{"test_questions": [[{"question": "The noise generated by a resistor depends upon", "opta": "its resistance value", "optb": "its operating temperature", "optc": "both its resistance value and operating temperature", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a superheterodyne receiver", "opta": "the IF stage has better selectivity than RF stage", "optb": "the RF stage has better selectivity than IF stage", "optc": "the RF stage has same selectivity than IF stage", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The function of an AM detector circuit is to", "opta": "rectify the input signal", "optb": "discard the carrier", "optc": "provide audio signal", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following should be used in order to prevent overloading or the last IF amplifier in a receiver?", "opta": "Variable selectivity", "optb": "Variable sensitivity", "optc": "Double conversion", "optd": "Squelch", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Most popular IF for receivers tuning to 540 to 1650 kHz is", "opta": "433 kHz", "optb": "455 kHz", "optc": "545 kHz", "optd": "555 kHz", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a broadcast superheterodyne receiver", "opta": "the local oscillator operates below the signal frequency", "optb": "local oscillator frequency is normally double the IF", "optc": "RF amplifier normally works at kHz above the carrier frequency", "optd": "mixer input must be tuned to the signal frequency", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A duplexer is a device used to", "opta": "feed more than one receiver from a single antenna", "optb": "connect two transmitters to the same antenna", "optc": "connect a receiver and a transmitter to the same antenna", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A heterodyne frequency changer is called a", "opta": "Modulator", "optb": "Mixer", "optc": "Demodulator", "optd": "Frequency translator", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "RF amplifiers are used in radio receivers for", "opta": "improved image frequency rejection", "optb": "improved rejection of adjacent unwanted signals", "optc": "prevention of re-radiation of the local oscillator through the antenna of the receiver", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The sensitivity curve of a standard receiver is represented by", "opta": "curve A", "optb": "curve B", "optc": "curve C", "optd": "curve D", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which are the popular IF frequencies for microwave and radar receivers operating on frequencies in the range 1 to 10 GHz", "opta": "30, 60 and 70 kHz", "optb": "3, 6 and 7 kHz", "optc": "30, 60 and 70 MHz", "optd": "3, 6 and 7 GHz", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a ratio detector", "opta": "the linearity is worse than in a phase discriminator", "optb": "the output is twice that obtainable from a similar phase discriminator", "optc": "stabilization against signal strength variations is provided", "optd": "the circuit is the same as in a discriminator, except that the diodes are reversed", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Neutralization is used in RF amplifiers to", "opta": "stop oscillation", "optb": "increase bandwidth", "optc": "improve selectivity", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When fs is the signal frequency and fi is the intermediate frequency, then image frequency fsi is given by", "opta": "fsi = fs - 2fi", "optb": "fsi = fs + 2fi", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It is known that noise phase modulates the FM wave. As the noise side band frequency approaches the carrier frequency, the noise amplitude", "opta": "will increase", "optb": "will decrease", "optc": "will remain constant", "optd": "will reduce to negligible value", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a receiver, which of the following device has IF input but RF output?", "opta": "Demodulator", "optb": "Loudspeaker", "optc": "Audio amplifier", "optd": "Frequency changer", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Transistor are free from which type of noise?", "opta": "Resistance noise", "optb": "Partition noise", "optc": "Flicker noise", "optd": "Shot noise", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Standard AM radio broadcasts are confined to", "opta": "MF", "optb": "HF", "optc": "VHF", "optd": "UHF", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a radio receiver with simple AGC", "opta": "the highest AGC voltage is produced between stations", "optb": "the faster the AGC time constant, the more accurate the output", "optc": "an increase in signal strength produces more AGC", "optd": "the audio stage gain is normally controlled by AGC", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following cannot be used to demodulate SSB?", "opta": "Complete phase-shift generator", "optb": "Product detector", "optc": "Diode balanced modulator", "optd": "Bipolar transistor balanced modulator", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A transmitter serial current contains", "opta": "carrier frequencies", "optb": "audio frequencies", "optc": "radio frequencies", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a broadcast superheterodynes receiver having no RF amplifier, the loaded Q of the antenna coupling circuit is 100. If the intermediate frequency is 455 kHz. The image frequency at 25 MHz will be", "opta": "24.09 MHz", "optb": "24.54 MHz", "optc": "25.45 MHz", "optd": "25.91 MHz", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a communication system, noise is most likely to affect the signal", "opta": "at the transmitter", "optb": "in the channel", "optc": "in the information source", "optd": "at the destination", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The noise produced by a resistor is proportional to", "opta": "absolute temperature", "optb": "(absolute temperature)2", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a radio receiver, if the intermediate frequency is too high", "opta": "Selectivity will be poor", "optb": "Tracking difficulties will be least", "optc": "Adjacent channel rejection will improve", "optd": "All of the above will occur", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a superheterodyne receiver, the IF is 455 kHz. If it is tuned to  1200 kHz, the image frequency will be", "opta": "1655 kHz", "optb": "2110 kHz", "optc": "745 kHz", "optd": "910 kHz", "ans": "B", "explanation": "A signal (image) can interfere with a superheterodyne receiver if fits the following equation.\nImage = Signal  +/-  2 x I.F.\nWhich says that a signal has the capacity to interfere with a superhet receiver if its frequency is equal to the signal frequency (1200 kHz in our question) plus or minus twice the IF (455 kHz in our question).\nSo one possible image is: 1200 + ( 2 x 455 ) = 2110 kHz (possible).\nAnd the other: 1200 - ( 2 x 455 )  = 290 kHz (not likely)."}, {"question": "The selectivity of most receivers is determined largely by", "opta": "sensitivity", "optb": "characteristics of IF section", "optc": "antenna direction", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a superheterodyne receiver with an IF of 450 kHz is tuned to a signal at 1200 kHz. The image frequency is", "opta": "750 kHz", "optb": "990 kHz", "optc": "1650 kHz", "optd": "2100 kHz", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a broadcast superheterodynes receiver having no RF amplifier, the loaded Q of the antenna coupling circuit is 100. If the intermediate frequency is 455 kHz. The rejection ratio at 25 MHz will be", "opta": "1.116", "optb": "1.386", "optc": "2.116", "optd": "2.386", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "As compared to tuned radio frequency receivers which of the following is the advantage of using superheterodyne receivers?", "opta": "High gain and better sensitivity", "optb": "Better selectivity at high frequencies", "optc": "Stability", "optd": "Noise suppression", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a radio receiver, if the intermediate frequency is too low", "opta": "Image-frequency rejection will improve", "optb": "Selectivity will be too sharp", "optc": "The frequency selectivity of the local oscillator will have to be lowered", "optd": "All of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "FM amplifier in a superheterodyne receiver", "opta": "increases selectivity", "optb": "suppresses noise", "optc": "provides improved tracking", "optd": "improves the rejection of the image frequency", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Padders are used in a receiver to", "opta": "discard the carrier", "optb": "facilitate tracking", "optc": "filter the input signal", "optd": "suppress noise", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a radio receiver, the local oscillator is tuned to a frequency", "opta": "lower than the incoming frequency", "optb": "higher than the incoming frequency", "optc": "equal to incoming frequency", "optd": "any of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following oscillator is generally not used at VHF?", "opta": "Colpitts oscillator", "optb": "Clapp oscillator", "optc": "Armstrong oscillator", "optd": "Ultra Audio oscillator", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An unmodulated voltage 10 V effective is applied to a dioxide detector in which load resistance is 4 x 10-5 ohms. A micrometer shows that the rectified DC current in this resistance is 30 A. The input resistance of the detector is", "opta": "114 kW", "optb": "336 kW", "optc": "384 kW", "optd": "455 kW", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The output of a diode detector contains", "opta": "D.C. voltage", "optb": "modulating signal", "optc": "RF ripple", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following noise does not occur in transistors?", "opta": "Partition noise", "optb": "Shot noise", "optc": "Flicker noise", "optd": "Resistance noise", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Noise generated in a resistor is also known as", "opta": "partition noise", "optb": "white noise", "optc": "thermal noise", "optd": "shot noise", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is used to provide tracking between RF amplifier and local oscillator stages of receiver?", "opta": "Variable tuning inductor", "optb": "Ganged tuning inductor", "optc": "Variable capacitor", "optd": "Variable preset", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The selectivity of a radio receiver is", "opta": "its ability to reject adjacent unwanted signals", "optb": "its ability to amplify weak signals", "optc": "the frequency at which it gives maximum amplification to signal.", "optd": "its ability to suppress noise.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the intermediate frequency of a superheterodyne receiver falls within the tuning range of the receiver", "opta": "Unsuitability will occur", "optb": "Heterodyne whistles will be heard", "optc": "Tuning to the frequency band immediately adjacent to the intermediate frequency will become impossible", "optd": "All of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "EM 84 tube is used in radio receivers as", "opta": "audio amplifier", "optb": "RF amplifier", "optc": "full wave rectifier", "optd": "magic eye", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement about receivers is false?", "opta": "Double conversion is used to improve image rejection", "optb": "Double conversion is used to improve selectivity", "optc": "Variable sensitivity is used to improve selectivity", "optd": "Variable sensitivity is used to eliminate selective fading", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Modulated carrier power in FM", "opta": "increases with modulating signal power", "optb": "decreases with modulating signal power", "optc": "is independent of the modulating signal power", "optd": "none", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In superheterodyne receivers, the local oscillator is used to", "opta": "detect the modulating signal", "optb": "amplify the received modulated carrier", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is same in AM and FM receivers?", "opta": "Demodulator", "optb": "AGC", "optc": "IF amplifier", "optd": "All of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A notch filter is sometimes used in communication receivers to", "opta": "reduce receiver gain at some specific frequency", "optb": "increase receiver gain at some specific frequency", "optc": "made selectivity more precise", "optd": "spread the bandwidth", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following is not a useful quantity for comparing the noise performance of receivers?", "opta": "Noise figure", "optb": "Noise temperature", "optc": "Input noise voltage", "optd": "Equivalent noise resistance", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement about the amplitude limiter is not valid?", "opta": "Leak type bias must be used", "optb": "Output must be tuned", "optc": "The circuit is always biased in class C, by virtue of the leak type bias", "optd": "When the input increases past the threshold of limiting, the gain decreases to keep the output constant", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}